Guide to the Tavern Guild of San Francisco Records, 1961-1993
Tavern Guild of San Francisco Records,
1961-1993
1995-02
Tavern Guild of San Francisco
21 boxes, 2 folders
The Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society. San Francisco, California.
Minutes, correspondence, financial papers, membership materials, ephemera, photographs, and banners, 1962-1993 (11.25 linear feet), document the work of the Tavern Guild of San Francisco in promoting the interests of gay bars in San Francisco as well as the growth of the Tavern Guild into a well-known service and fundraising organization.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the GLBT Historical Society by Stanley Boyd in 1995.
Organizational History
The Tavern Guild of San Francisco (TGSF) was founded in 1962. The organization had its roots in an informal gathering of gay bar owners and employees who met regularly to socialize and to share news of interest to members of the gay bar community. Phil Doganiero, a bartender at the Suzy-Q bar on Polk Street, was elected the first president of the nascent organization; he was followed by others such as Bill Plath (owner of the D'Oak Room) and Darryl Glied (owner of the Jumpin' Frog). In
Wide Open Town: A History of Queer San Francisco to 1965
, historian Nan Boyd writes, The Tavern Guild had initially formed to bring business to alternating bars on typically slow Tuesday afternoons, and the original members stressed the importance of drinking--and gossip. But within its first year, TGSF instituted a number of policies that helped protect bartenders, bar owners, and patrons from continued problems. (p. 223) These problems included patrons who wrote bad checks, police harassment, Alcoholic Beverage Control (ABC) actions against bars, and the chronic unemployment faced by bartenders whose jobs were subject to the whims of patrons and the actions of police. While the core of the Tavern Guild was bar owners and employees, members of the homophile movement were involved (like Hal Call of the Mattachine Society) and helped provide the Tavern Guild with an organizational structure in its early years.
Along with protecting gay bar owners and employees, the Tavern Guild reached out as a charitable organization and staged fundraising events for homophile organizations like the Mattachine Society, the Daughters of Bilitis, and the Society for Individual Rights, and, later in the 1960s, for non-gay organizations like the United Farm Workers and the American Civil Liberties Union.
Funds were most often raised at events such as auctions, dances, and other social gatherings. Perhaps the most important of these events, the annual Beaux Arts Ball, was first held in October 1963. At the October 1965 Beaux Arts Ball, Jos Sarria was named queen of the ball; in a Napoleonic gesture, Sarria responded by declaring himself "Empress." The Empress title stuck and at the following year's ball a new Empress was elected to lead the recently formed Imperial Court--an official "project" of the Tavern Guild that became the locus of many social and benevolent activities.
The San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation (SFTGF) was created to be the organization's fundraising and philanthropic arm. The foundation identified organizations and causes worthy of financial support and distributed funds to those organizations and causes. The SFTGF consisted merely of a board of directors, so the actual events, though sponsored by the Foundation, were organized and staffed by volunteers from the TGSF membership. While both organizations had non-profit status, the SFTGF was a tax-exempt entity, so it was not allowed to give money to the TGSF, except as seed money for fund-raising activities. The SFTGF spearheaded several fundraising and service-oriented projects, including the Godfathers (ca. 1984), Operation Concern (1974), and the Community Thrift Store (1982), the latter two of which eventually were spun off into independent organizations.
The membership and, consequently, the influence of the Tavern Guild grew from the 1960s through the early 1980s. From the handful of members in the early 1960s, in June 1980 the Tavern Guild claimed a member base of at least 184 individuals and 86 businesses, mostly gay and lesbian bars. Other gay and lesbian communities around the country adopted the Tavern Guild model and name in the 1970s and 1980s. For many reasons, including a pronounced generational divide and the widespread death and community fragmentation as a result of the AIDS epidemic, the Tavern Guild lost members and influence throughout the 1980s. The organization disbanded about 1995.
Reflecting upon the source of the longstanding power and influence of the Tavern Guild, bar owner and Tavern Guild member Rikki Streicher said in an interview with Nan Boyd, The Tavern Guild was probably singly the reason why bars achieved a success politically. Because a buck is the bottom line at all times. And the bars had commanded an enormous amount of money in terms of the city. So when they began to invite politicians to their meetings, the politicians realized that here's an organized group and that, number one, they have money and, number two, they have votes. (
Wide Open Town: A History of Queer San Francisco to 1965, p.226
)
Scope and Content of Collection
Minutes, correspondence, financial papers, membership materials, ephemera, photographs, and banners, 1962-1993 (11.25 linear feet), document the work of the Tavern Guild of San Francisco (TGSF) in promoting the interests of gay bars in San Francisco as well as the growth of the Tavern Guild into a well-known service and fundraising organization. The collection reveals how the organization was run, how it changed through the years, who its members were, and its activities, goals, and methods. It also gives insight into the San Francisco bar scene and the changing concerns of the gay community in San Francisco from the 1960s through the 1980s.
The first series contains documents such as constitutions, by-laws, and organizational histories that provide an overview of the organization and its mission. The Meeting Minutes Series reveals who was active in the organization, how it was run, and concerns of members, as well as what events, programs, and projects the Tavern Guild was involved in. Series 9, Administrative and Miscellaneous, contains a few items related to the running of the Tavern Guild office.
The third series, Correspondence, is relatively small (nine folders) and contains a wide range of topics. The Financial Series includes financial reports and other summary financial data as well as a sampling of receipts and invoices. Income tax returns and applications for tax-exempt status can also be found here. The Membership Series could be mined for data regarding the demographics of San Francisco bars. Included on the membership forms are the names, addresses, and owners of bars, and the names, addresses, and places of employment of bar employees. Meeting attendance lists show who attended each meeting.
Series 6 and 7 concern events, programs, and projects the Tavern Guild of San Francisco and San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation were involved in. Some were ongoing or annual, such as the Beaux Arts Ball and Community Thrift Store, and others were more short term. Financial documentation, correspondence, and ephemera comprise the bulk of these series. Photographs of some events can be found in series 10, Photographs.
The collection is divided into 11 series:
General
Meeting Minutes
Correspondence
Financial
Membership
Events
Programs and Projects
Political Subject Files
Administrative and Miscellaneous
Photographs
Banners
One box of legal-sized materials is found at the end of the collection (box 20).
Separated Material
Items removed the collection totaled about two cartons and included the following materials:
Ephemera: Flyers for events and bars were removed to the Ephemera Collection.
Duplicates: Duplicate financial information was removed from the collection, but examples of receipts as well as summarized financial statements were retained.
Related Material at the Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society
Scott Bishop Papers, 1990-11
Matthew Brown Papers, 2001-23
Robert Cramer Papers, 1996-19
Golden Gate Business Association, 1990-06
Henri I. Leleu Papers, 1997-13
Phyllis Lyon and Del Martin Papers, 1993-13
Don Lucas Papers, 1997-25
People's Fund Records, 1988-06
Q.T. Bar Records and Artifacts, 1997-70
David Root Slides, 1990-07
Jos Sarria Papers, 1996-01
Wide Open Town History Project Records
GLBTHS Sites Database
GLBTHS Poster Collection: bar and Beaux Arts Ball posters
GLBTHS Ephemera Collection: Organizations/Groups; Recurring Events; Sites
GLBTHS Oral History Collection: Don Lucas; Jos Sarria; Phyllis Lyon and Del Martin; Otto Bremerman; Bill Plath
Container List
A copy of the collection register is kept in the first box of the collection (1/21).
Box 20 contains legal sized material.
- General, 1964-1993, n.d., Series 1:; 13 Folders
  This series includes the constitution and by-laws of the Tavern Guild of San Francisco and the San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation, a history of the organizations, information about their establishment, relationship, and boards of directors. The awards include two plaques: a Cable Car Award and an award from the Godfather's Service Fund.
  - History and Pamphlets, 1966, n.d. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Constitution and By-Laws, 1969-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Constitution and By-Laws, Legal Size, 1970, n.d. (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Constitution and By-Laws Proposed Changes, 1967, 1982, n.d. (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Constitution and By-Laws Proposed Changes, Legal Size, 1970, n.d. (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Articles of Incorporation, 1964 (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Member Guidelines, n.d. (Box-folder 1/4)
  - San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws, 1972, 1981, n.d. (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Minutes of First Meeting of Incorporators and First Board of Directors of San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation, 1972 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Coexistence Rules and "Fiscal Agents" Memorandum, 1982, n.d. (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Tavern Guild of San Francisco Board and Elections, 1975-1993 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Awards 1/2, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Awards 2/2, 1982, 1989 (Box 21)
  - Rules and Regulations of Peninsula Guild, n.d. (Box-folder 1/10)
- Meeting Minutes, 1962-1993, n.d., Series 2:; 3 Boxes
  This series includes meeting minutes for both board meetings and general meetings, and door sign-in sheets for general meetings. Minutes and attendance sheets have been filed separately, each chronologically by year. Because the general meeting usually occurred the same day as the board meeting, the minutes of the two meetings were combined and distributed together, in a document that the Tavern Guild called its "newsletter." These newsletters often included enclosures of various kinds, including flyers, financial statements, memoranda or letters, and bad check lists. We have tried to keep these items in the Meeting Minutes Series because they were distributed with them. Handwritten notes from meetings or first drafts of minutes have been kept, when these existed, and filed with the final copy.
  A wide range of topics are covered in this series: administration of the organization as well as events, programs, and projects.
  - Meeting Minutes (Box-folder 1/11-4/4)
    - Spiral Notebook of Minutes and Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - n.d. (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Meeting Sign-In Sheets (Box-folder 4/5-4/11)
    - 1963-1964 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - [1969]-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 4/6)
    - 1981-1984 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 4/11)
- Correspondence, 1964-1993, n.d., Series 3:; 9 Folders
  This series includes incoming and outgoing letters and telegrams arranged chronologically. While an effort was made to keep enclosures with correspondence, some may have been separated into other series. Correspondence about donations made by the Tavern Guild is included in this series, but receipts and items treated as invoices by the Tavern Guild were removed to the Financial Series. For example, a letter asking for a donation is in the Correspondence Series unless a check number and amount paid is noted on it, in which case it is in the Financial Series.
  Correspondents include lawyers, Tavern Guild members, other community groups, and vendors. Additional correspondence with Accountants and the Internal Revenue service may be found in the Financial Series. A notebook containing a small amount of correspondence can be found in the first folder of the Meeting Minutes Series.
  - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - 1970-1972 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - 1973-1974 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - 1975 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - 1976-1980 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - 1981-1986 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - 1987-1993, n.d. (Box-folder 5/5)
- Financial, 1964-1993, n.d., Series 4:; 3 Boxes
  This series includes financial documentation for both TGSF and SFTGF. Due to the nature of the relationship between the two organizations, it was often difficult to separate the material intellectually and impossible to separate it physically because it is printed on the same pieces of paper. Types of material include monthly, quarterly, and yearly financial reports, check registers, statements, invoices, and receipts. Topics include the Hungarian Hall and 170 Valencia purchases, tax-exempt status, and donations made by the TGSF/SFTGF. Their fiscal year was July 1 through June 30.
  This series was weeded extensively of receipts and invoices, with a small number retained as examples. The summarized information, such as financial statements, was retained in all cases, except duplicates. Financial documentation that pertains to events, projects, and programs of the organization can also be found in the Events Series and the Programs and Projects Series. Because the non-profit and tax-exempt status of the organization depended on the money-making activities of many of these projects, however, some of this documentation is in this series. One folder of carbon copies of receipts, mostly for membership dues, can be found in the Membership Series.
  Items that were treated as invoices by the Tavern Guild are filed as such. For example, a letter asking for a donation is in the Correspondence Series unless the check number and amount paid is noted on it, in which case it is in the Financial Series. Thank-you letters for donations are in the Correspondence Series, but receipts for donations are in the Financial Series, even though they are often very similar in format to letters. Correspondence with accountants and the IRS that came with the financial material was left in this series. Additional correspondence with accountants may be found in the Correspondence Series.
  - List of Grants and Other Donations Made by Tavern Guild/Foundation by Year, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - 170 Valencia Purchase, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Hungarian Hall Purchase, 1987 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Mission Rebels in Action, Inc. Pacific Gas and Electric (PGE) Bills, 1968 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Bank Documentation, 1971-1989, n.d. (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Atlas Savings and Loan Passbooks for SFTGF Building Fund, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Correspondence with Accountants, 1974-1984 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - IRS Correspondence, 1974-1987 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - State of California Tavern Guild of San Francisco Tax Status, 1964-1987 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - State of California San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation Tax Status, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Forms CT-2, 1974-1983 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - TGSF and SFTGF Documents for Tax-Exempt Status, 1974-1990 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Tax Returns (Box-folder 6/1-6/9)
    - TGSF Forms 199 and 990 (Box-folder 6/1-6/4)
      - 1978-1983 (Box-folder 6/1)
      - 1985, 1987 (Box-folder 6/2)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 6/3)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - SFTGF Forms 199, 990, CT-2 (Box-folder 6/5-6/9)
      - 1973-1981 (Box-folder 6/5)
      - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 6/6)
      - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6/7)
      - 1987-1988 (Box-folder 6/8)
      - 1989-1990 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - General Financial (Box-folder 6/10-8/6)
    - 1964-1966 (Box-folder 6/10)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 6/11)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 6/12)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 6/13)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 6/14)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 6/15)
    - 1972 1/2 (Box-folder 6/16)
    - 1972 2/2 (Box-folder 20/4)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 6/17)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 6/18)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 20/5)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 7/3)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 7/4)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 7/7)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 7/8)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 7/9)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 7/10)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Foundation Audit, 1985 (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Financial Report 1985 San Francisco Tavern Guild Foundation, 1985 (Box-folder 7/13)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 7/14)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - 1991-1993, n.d. (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Check Register, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 8/6)
- Membership, [1962]-1992, n.d., Series 5:; 6 Boxes
  This series includes membership applications, membership lists, copies of receipts from 1974 membership dues, and examples of membership cards and signs. Business memberships were for bars or other businesses and individual memberships were for employees of bars. Memberships could be regular or associate, and during some years there were honorary members as well. Associate and honorary members were not eligible to vote.
  The applications are a particularly rich source for the history of the demographics of San Francisco bars. It is possible to trace the names and addresses of bars as they came and went, the names of owners and managers of different bars, the names and addresses of employees, and where they worked. This series also shows some of the Tavern Guild's membership procedures.
  - Membership Applications, New and Renewal (Box-folder 8/7-14/5)
    - Business (Box-folder 8/7-10/10)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 8/7)
      - 1972 (Box-folder 8/8)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 8/9)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 8/10)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 9/1)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 9/2)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 9/3)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 9/4)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 9/5)
      - 1981 (Box-folder 9/6)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 9/7)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 9/8)
      - 1984 (Box-folder 9/9)
      - 1984, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 10/1)
      - 1985 (Box-folder 10/2)
      - 1985, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 10/3)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 10/4)
      - 1987 (Box-folder 10/5)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 10/6)
      - 1988, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 10/7)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 10/8)
      - 1989, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 10/9)
      - 1990, n.d. (Box-folder 10/10)
    - Individual (Box-folder 10/11-14/5)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 10/11)
      - 1972, A-K (Box-folder 10/12)
      - 1972, L-Z (Box-folder 10/13)
      - 1973, A-F (Box-folder 10/14)
      - 1973, G-O (Box-folder 11/1)
      - 1973, P-Z (Box-folder 11/2)
      - 1974, A-M (Box-folder 11/3)
      - 1974, N-Z (Box-folder 11/4)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 11/5)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 11/6)
      - 1977, A-K (Box-folder 12/1)
      - 1977, L-Z (Box-folder 12/2)
      - 1978, A-K (Box-folder 12/3)
      - 1978, L-Z (Box-folder 12/4)
      - 1979, A-K (Box-folder 12/5)
      - 1979, L-Z (Box-folder 12/6)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 12/7)
      - 1981 (Box-folder 13/1)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 13/2)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 13/3)
      - 1984 (Box-folder 13/4)
      - 1984, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 13/5)
      - 1985 (Box-folder 13/6)
      - 1985, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 13/7)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 13/8)
      - 1987 (Box-folder 14/1)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 14/2)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 14/3)
      - 1989, Associate Memberships (Box-folder 14/4)
      - 1990, n.d. (Box-folder 14/5)
  - Membership Lists, [1962]-1992 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - Carbon Copies of Receipts (mostly membership dues), 1974 (Box-folder 14/7)
  - Address Updates, n.d. (Box-folder 14/8)
  - Member Communications, 1973-1991 (Box-folder 14/9)
  - Membership Cards, 1985, 1987, n.d. (Box-folder 14/10)
  - Member Bar Signs, n.d. (Box-folder 14/11)
  - Blank Membership Forms, n.d. (Box-folder 14/12)
- Events, 1961-1993, Series 6:; 1 Box, 7 Folders
  This series contains budgets, financial statements, receipts, contracts, agreements, notes, correspondence, ephemera, seating charts, maps, a button, and clippings relating to events with which the Tavern Guild was involved. Included are events put on by the Tavern Guild, such as the Beaux Arts Ball, Picnic, and Coronation, as well as events that they participated in but did not sponsor. More information about events may be found in the Financial Series, Correspondence Series, and Meeting Minutes Series. Godfathers' events are in the Godfathers subseries of the Programs and Projects Series.
  - Beaux Arts Ball (Box-folder 14/13-15/2)
    - 1966-1974 (Box-folder 14/13)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 14/14)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 14/15)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 14/16)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 14/17)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 14/18)
    - 1981-1984 (Box-folder 15/1)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 20/6)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - Picnic (Box-folder 15/3-15/20)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 15/3)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 15/4)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 15/5)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 15/6)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 15/7)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 15/8)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 15/9)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 15/10)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 15/11)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 15/12)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 15/13)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 15/14)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 15/15)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 15/16)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 15/17)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 15/18)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 15/19)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 15/20)
  - Coronation, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 15/21)
  - Circus-Circus, 1982 (Box-folder 15/22)
  - Gala, 1986 (Box-folder 15/23)
  - No On 6, 1978 (Box-folder 15/24)
  - Shanti Project/KS Foundation Fundraiser, 1983 (Box-folder 15/25)
  - S.F. AIDS Fund/Shanti Project Benefit, 1983 (Box-folder 15/26)
  - Reno Trip, 1973 (Box-folder 15/27)
  - Auction 10-8-73, 1973 (Box-folder 20/7)
  - Metropolitan Community Church National Conference Tavern Guild Souvenir Guide, 1974 (Box-folder 15/28)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 15/29)
  - General Event Information (Box-folder 15/30-15/34)
    - Security, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 15/30)
    - Insurance, 1983 (Box-folder 15/31)